Oak Street Methodist Church (Binghamton, N.Y.) Records
Oak Street Methodist Church (Binghamton, N.Y.) Records
1913-1976
Oak Street Methodist Church (Binghamton, N.Y.)
2 linear ft.
Methodist church in Binghamton, New York; in existence 1891-1976. Collection includes attendance records (1971), material pertaining to church history (1913-1974), reports (1968-1976), correspondence (1966-76), and financial records (1966-1976).
149413
Biographical History
Oak Street Methodist Church was located in Binghamton, New York; it was also known as Oak Street Methodist Episcopal Church and Oak Street United Methodist Church. The church began in 1891 as a summer Sunday school, and the building was dedicated in 1893. The church was located at 219 Oak Street (corner of Oak and Gaines Streets) in Binghamton, with the parsonage nearby at 3 Elm Street. Faced with declining membership and problems related to its inner city location, the church closed in 1976.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Oak Street Methodist Church (Binghamton, N.Y.) Records consists of business files, correspondence, financial files and legal files.
Business files includes a church history and related material. Correspondence contains general correspondence spanning the late 1960s and early 1970s. Financial files contains cancelled checks and check stubs, financial reports, and paid bills. Legal files contains insurance records for the building.
There are also unprocessed additions which are not yet open to researchers.
Arrangement of the Collection
Business files are arranged alphabetically by type. All other series are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to church and clergy in and around Central New York. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; New York State; Oak Street Methodist Church (Binghamton, N.Y.) -- Archives.; Oak Street Methodist Episcopal Church (Binghamton, N.Y.) -- Archives.; Oak Street United Methodist Church (Binghamton, N.Y.) -- Archives.; Church records and registers -- New York (State) -- Binghamton.; Methodist Church -- New York (State) -- Binghamton.; Methodists -- New York (State) -- Binghamton.; Methodists -- United States.; New York (State) -- Religious life and customs.; Church registers.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Reports.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Business files
  - Attendance records, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Church history (Box 1)
  - Material pertaining to church history, 1913-1974 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1968-1976 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1966-1976 (Box 1)
- Financial files
  - Cancelled checks, 1967-1976; 10 folders (Box 1)
  - Check stubs, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Financial reports, 1967-1976 (Box 1)
  - Financial secretary's records, 1965-1976 (Box 1)
  - Official church treasurer's records, 1966-1975 (Oversize 1)
  - Paid bills, 1967-1974; 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Paid bills, 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Legal files
  - Insurance papers, 1965-1976 (Box 3)